Welcome to the height of spring.
We've come to the New Forest to see for ourselves the arrival of spring in the British countryside.
And to celebrate, we're off on our own little spring break, so I've got everything that we're going to need here in this rucksack, including our tent.
So, just waiting for Julia.
Here she is.
Oh, my word!
Hello!
Hello, love.
What are you doing?
What do you mean?
I thought we were camping.
Have you not heard of glamping?
Glamping?
Glamping is glamorous camping.
It's camping but with some comforts.
Well, I love your flowers.
They're nice.
Come on, I'll show you how.
Brilliant.
Do you like the colour?
It's lovely.
It's called nude.
Some people call it beige.
I've got that much stuff!
What have you got your frying pan for?
I thought we'd need the whole lot.
I'll show you how this is done.
You don't need any of that.
Your saggy old tent's going to look very tired.
So, spring has sprung, my lovely.
Hasn't it just?
Here we are, in the New Forest, absolutely delightful.
There's loads of stuff we can do.
We'll have a great spring adventure.
'I'm going lobster potting to catch something luxurious for our lunch.'
'And spring is the start of the sea angling season, 'to see if I can catch an elusive sea bass.'
'We'll be venturing into the Forest to record that spring sensation, the dawn chorus.'
'And it's the perfect time to do that, 'because this is the weekend of International Dawn Chorus Day 'and spring is the best time of year 'to hear the birds in all their orchestral glory.'
I do love a good dawn chorus.
But getting up at 5am, it's so hard.
Don't worry, I'll wake you up.
And of course, the others are up to all sorts of bits and pieces as well, aren't they?
They're all over the country doing spring things.
How do you know when spring has sprung?
Is the first time you see daffodils like these?
Or the first time you hear the call of the cuckoo?
With so many different ways out there of telling, I'll be looking when nature decides whether it's spring and why.
Spring is all about new beginnings and new opportunities, so I'm out and about looking for ideas to expand my farming business.
And at the moment, top of the list is camel racing.
Well, these are the kind of spring vegetables you'd have found in shops years ago, but now all this is available.
We seem to have lost the idea of seasonal food, so what's the impact been?
I'll be investigating.
And I've come to one of the darkest places in the UK for an unrivalled look at the universe.
The New Forest National Park was created in 2005.
It covers more than 140,000 acres of woodland, coast and wilderness heaths.
And in keeping with the record numbers of us choosing to holiday in the UK, we're making our way through the Forest to experience our own special version of camping.
Spring really is the perfect time to see the New Forest at its best.
You've got all the bluebells, you've got the lime green buds popping through on the trees.
Crocuses, daffodils, blossoms all starting to bud.
Smile and say, spring.
Spring.
And new life as well, with loads of lambs around, and if we're lucky, we might be able to spot some of the New Forest foals.
I hope so.
But of course, you know who the expert at spotting spring is?
It's our James.
The worst winter in 30 years prompted us all to ask, when will spring begin?
So did it arrive any later than normal this year?
And what marks the start of the season?
Well, I'm on a mission to find out.
According to the calendar, spring officially starts at the vernal equinox, and that's when the sun crosses the equator for the first time in that year.
And that normally happens at the 20th or 21st March, depending on the year.
But when is it to the rest of you?
I think spring is here when the crocuses are in full bloom.
Lambs, daffodils.
Daffodils coming out.
I always see them on my drive to work and it really represents spring for me.
Easter bunnies.
Lambs in the fields.
Probably the daffodils and the crocuses coming out.
Hopefully a bit of sunshine.
Blossom, sunshine, cutting the grass.
For so many of us, it's the daffodil that's that iconic spring flower.
And on this site right here, we've got one of the largest wild populations in the whole country.
Andy Bakere, the warden here, has been monitoring this explosion of springtime colour for years.
So, Andy, what have you noticed about the flowering of these guys this year?
They're probably about two weeks later than they are normally.
So the majority were in bloom round about 30th March, which is round about two weeks later than they would be normally.
Are they your, kind of, key plant for your indicator of spring?
Yes, absolutely.
When you see the trumpet of the daffodil and a bumble bee buzzing away, beavering away inside it, you know, that's a real indication of spring for me.
Two indicators at the same time?
Absolutely.
Extra bonus points!
So the daffodil, that harbinger of spring, was up to ten days late here in Devon, flowering on or around 30th March.
But there are some signs of spring that really aren't that obvious or in-your-face.
As I'm in Devon, it would be a crime not to go to the beach.
Now, it's been a few years since I've been rock pooling, so today I'm being shown the ropes by some junior rangers.
Apparently, finding a starfish is one sign that spring has begun.
While their search goes on, the warden here, James, has already made a discovery.
So what have we got over here?
Well, underneath this rock, I just found a little earlier, some dog whelk eggs that have been laid up there by the whelks.
When you see your first eggs, you know that winter's coming to an end?
Yes, that's right.
So it's daylight, it's not temperature, or anything like that that triggers them on to doing it?
No, because the temperature in the pools lags behind the temperature on the land.
What else would you see in this environment that would make you think spring has sprung?
The fish that come into their own at this time of year are things like the really common rock pool fish, which is this blenny here.
Never a peacock, a little bit more subdued, but definitely in spring, they're brighter coloured than you'd find in the winter.
So why do they change colour in spring?
It's to attract mates.
Like getting dressed up on a Friday night?
Exactly.
Putting on your best frock.
Yes.
The junior rangers have got buckets full of sea life now.
But are there any starfish?
We got a big crab.
Yes.
And a velvet something crab.
Uh-huh.
And then the catfish.
I found a tiny crab but I don't know where he is.
Is he hidden underneath?
There he is.
That weeny one there.
Look at that!
And what's in this one?
That's a devil crab.
That's an enormous one.
Did you pick that up with your hands?
You're braver than me.
I touched that mini crab.
It was so cute.
Well, plenty of evidence of spring, but no starfish today.
So, James, I want you to tell me on the calendar, as I hear starfish are really good indicator of spring, when spring's sprung under water?
Well, for me this year, we found loads of starfish around March 12th.
So for me, that was spring under the waves.
So one of the first indicators of spring?
I think in the cold weather, they've gone back out to sea.
Decided it's winter!
Now, I know my study's not exactly scientific, but I'm really fascinated about all the different ways that you can measure when spring has actually sprung.
With a really harsh winter, with such late snows, one of the things I'm really interested in is how it's affected things like hibernating mammals.
The Beer Caves in Devon are a vast complex of underground caverns created by centuries of quarrying.
They're also where eight species of bat like to hibernate, including the very rare horseshoe bat.
What can these guys tell us about spring?
They already seem to be stirring.
They are stirring slightly.
These are probably the very last of the bats to be hanging on in here.
Very shortly, they'll be going out and starting to feed again.
As soon as the brilliant spring weather starts, they'll be off out, foraging.
So as soon as the temperature rises, I'm guessing, in here, that they go out?
Yes.
So in the bat calendar, is it fair to say that spring has already sprung, or half sprung?
I think it's just springing, yes.
Certainly if you're out at night now, at dusk, you see the bats flying around.
So what date to the bats of Beer suggest to Fiona that spring began this year?
I'm going to put that, if I may, after Easter, because down in Devon here, it became glorious in the middle of that week there.
OK, so spring for bats is later than it is for everyone else.
I would say so this year, yes.
The sea life in our rock pools and the sleepy bats of Beer each have a different story to tell about the start of spring.
But for me, spring has never really sprung until you get one of these trees that just completely enrobes itself in fluorescent pink and white and all shades in between.
And it's not just me that thinks it.
The National Trust actually gauges spring by when the first magnolias come out.
And I happen to know that these magnolias started flowering on the 2nd March.
So what does my little calendar of the signs of spring tell me?
Well, I can say in the long term, really not that much.
But looking at it, particularly this year after we've had such a long and such a harsh winter, it certainly seems like this year at least, Mother Nature seems that little bit reluctant to cast off her woolly jumper, and like most of us, get out there and have an amazing summer.
But when she gets here, it's truly spectacular.
Well, thankfully now that spring has finally sprung, it's the perfect time for fishing and I fancy lobster for lunch.
I'm sure you do, but I'm heading to the beach to try and catch something for the whole Countryfile team, who are joining us for breakfast tomorrow.
Spring heralds the start of the shore angling season, so I'm meeting Malcolm Stote and his son Dan.
Malcolm fishes for the England team, so if anyone can help me land a big one, it's going to be him.
Malcolm, how are you doing?
All right?
Not too bad, thanks.
What are you using here?
Dried worm, this is.
It's what we dug here this morning.
We're aiming for what?
What fish?
Anything really, but it's the good thing about the sea angling, you don't really know what you'll catch.
The best thing would be a nice bass.
Is she all ready to go?
Yes, she's ready to go.
You just get that round to there, like that.
Yes.
That's it.
Pull it up against the rod.
All right.
And if you put it behind you.
Duck, everyone!
There you go.
Just have to stand and wait now.
And that's it?
That's it.
To be fair, I haven't got too long here.
What are the chances of catching a sea bass in 40 minutes?
Possible.
Nothing.
'Not a nibble.
But thankfully, 'Malcolm has already caught some this morning.'
Is it the case then, Malcolm, with whatever you catch, you can keep?
Not really.
I mean, if you look at this one here, I know this one's way undersize.
Our club size is 41 centimetres.
Now, this one measures at 29.
I've got one in the bucket that I would like to show you as well.
The thing to watch is you've got some really sharp spines on the back.
None of it's poisonous, but they'll make you bleed a bit.
Now, this is a big fish, so...
It's a bigger fish, yeah.
So that one's 36, 37, yes?
The Government size, this is 36, which says you can legally keep it.
They are nice to eat.
That is their downfall, to be honest.
But everybody knows that bass is a nice fish to eat.
Right, then, so these three are going to go back in?
Yes.
Well, no luck catching something from here for breakfast.
But I do have a plan B up my sleeve.
I wonder if Julia's having any more luck.
I'm hoping to trump Matt with my fishing skills and I think I've got the slight advantage because I'm actually going out to sea.
Hello, how are you doing?
Not too bad.
Good, good.
I hope it's a good day for some lobster.
I've got lunch to make.
'Now it's spring, the waters of the Solent have warmed up, 'meaning lobsters are on the move and ready to catch.
'Stephen Turner's been lobster fishing these waters for nearly 30 years.'
Now, it's been a really cold winter, hasn't it?
So lobsters don't like cold water?
No.
That's why the season's only just starting now.
It should have started a month ago, really.
Nothing in there.
Nothing in that one.
Ah!
Let's check.
Nothing.
Here we go.
Look at that.
So we've got a nice big crab and that looks like a good size lobster.
He's going to do it, isn't he?
Look at that.
That, ladies and gentlemen, is lunch.
There we go.
Number one...
Number two...
'The freshly baited pots are laid again ready for Stephen to return tomorrow.'
Stephen, it's been a pleasure.
Thank you very much.
Not a problem.
With the crustaceans caught, I'm making my way to Michael's mother-in-law's to get them prepared for lunch.
Hello, Julia.
Hello.
Oh, Julia!
There we go, look.
We've got a lobster.
Wonderful.
But a Brucey bonus as well.
Brilliant.
What you've got to do now is show me what to do with them.
Do you want me to do that for you?
Please.
They go into boiling water...
..For 12 minutes.
A lot of people think this is very cruel.
No, it's not actually because they die instantly.
Whatever Matt's got for lunch, Joan, it's not going to be as delicious as this.
And I've also got you some lovely dressed crab.
The crab as well.
Little extra.
Delicious.
Well, I didn't have much luck at the beach.
Have a bit more over there(!)
There is plenty here for breakfast because, unlike Julia, I've got the interest of the whole team at heart.
There you go.
Get your chops around that.
HE CHUCKLES This is pretty frantic!
Well, Graham, these are the most fantastic brown trout.
Wow.
There's a few in there to look at.
What age are these, then?
These fish are about three to three-and-a-half-years-old.
So, a bit more food in a few more months and they'll be ready for smoking and serving up with a few scrambled eggs.
Do you want to pop them back in?
Yeah.
They're so athletic!
They're very muscular fish.
They are absolutely beautiful I'd love to try some but I haven't got time to smoke them.
Well, I think we can find some that we made earlier in the fridge.
You can sort us out.
That's good news.
Can I feed a few more of these fish before I go?
It's quite an experience, isn't it?
I've worked up an appetite so it's time to eat.
What better spot than here deep in the forest?
The wanderer returns!
How are you doing?
All right?
Don't say I'm never whip up a meal for you.
Look at that - your favourite.
Absolutely gorgeous.
Now, that...
Let me just compare it with what I was thinking of.
Cheese sandwiches.
Yeah.
This is about as fresh as you can get.
I caught that lobster about an hour ago.
Did you?
Yeah, have a taste.
I mean, it's really the definition of seasonal food.
So, we've got lobster here, crabs as well.
Little bit of extra.
Yeah.
This was a Brucey bonus.
I wasn't expecting it.
We got lots, actually, lots of nice big crabs.
Well, John's been to find out what else traditionally should be on our spring plates.
For hundreds of years, we Brits have been importing exotic food from all over the globe.
Bananas, for example, first arrived here in the time of Queen Victoria.
But since the end of the Second World War, we've taken it all a step further.
Now, we're demanding our own traditional fruit and vegetables all year round even though they're only in season naturally for a few weeks every year.
So, we get our runner beans from Kenya and new potatoes from Egypt.
It's all very convenient.
But is it right?
The fact that a lot of things are imported that maybe should not be imported and we should just live on what we get in season and be happy with that.
We've got very good farmland here.
All over the countryside and we can actually make our own food if we wanted to.
As long as it's on the shelf, I'm happy with it.
But we live in a global economy and I'm afraid that there's about eight million of us in London and we all need a bit of food in the evening.
40 years ago, if you'd been shopping for fruit and veg in spring, you're choice would have been fairly limited.
Today there's endless choice.
It's relatively cheap and as far as food's concerned, there's no such thing as seasons any more.
"More's the pity," say some.
I'm on my way now to meet Vernon Mascarenhas who supplies seasonal fruit and vegetables to some of the finest hotels and restaurants in London.
He's convinced that eating seasonally is good for us.
It's 8am and Vernon has deliveries to make to some of the most demanding chefs in the capital.
Good morning.
Nice to see you.
What have you got on the van today, then?
Right, this is what we harvested yesterday.
So, we have some black cabbage here.
We have some Cheltenham beetroot.
Some Swiss Chard.
Red Swiss Chard.
And there we have some purple sprouting broccoli.
Can I help you with a box?
Where are we going?
Just up here to Henry at Racine.
So you believe in seasonal vegetables, then?
Tell him what's coming in season and he has it on his menu the next day.
You serve seasonal stuff in the restaurant?
The whole restaurant's driven by seasonality.
It's what brings in the changes to the menu.
Here's some black cabbage.
Fantastic.
And some Cheltenham beetroot.
Thanks a lot, Vernon.
See you.
Bye.
So, what next, Vernon?
So we've got our fantastic asparagus.
Fresh.
First of the season.
But isn't it a bit old-fashioned, don't you think?
To be waiting for the seasons when you can get food anytime, anywhere, from any place?
I think it's lovely.
The anticipation.
So, for eight weeks a year we have asparagus.
Then, that's it, we have to wait a whole year for any more.
Nothing like the taste of British asparagus.
Absolutely.
Here you go, Matt.
And now strawberries.
First of the English season.
A lot of people can't wait for a strawberry.
They want one at Christmas.
They don't taste of anything then.
These are beautifully delicious English ones.
They'll be on a table at lunchtime.
Absolutely.
I know you're in a hurry to get them all delivered.
How many London restaurants will get fresh seasonal food today?
We'll do about 200 but we don't just do restaurants.
We do shops as well so people can come out and buy it.
So it's not elitist, buying seasonal?
Absolutely not.
But there are times of year when it's pretty boring stuff that's being grown in our fields.
Broccoli, curly kale, things like that.
It is seasonal.
You get celeriac, you have parsnips.
There are over winter apples and pears.
You've got quinces.
It's just a different season, that's all.
Hey, what have you got for me today?
Hey, Sanjay.
There's strawberries.
Beautiful.
First of the season.
Great.
Anything else for me?
I've got some sprouting broccoli, Swiss chard...
Seasonal food champions, like Vernon, question shipping-in supplies like these new potatoes from Egypt which they believe they are using up valuable water resources in an already dry region.
For them, it's best to wait until we can grow our own.
Eating seasonal food out of season doesn't necessarily mean shipping it from abroad.
These days, we can extend our seasons here in the UK.
July to October were always the months to eat tomatoes but now vast heated greenhouses mean we can grow them between February and November.
So, it's time to set out our stall.
Is flying in produce worse for the planet than heating greenhouses here in the UK with fossil fuels?
Today, I am going to be marking up my prices not in pounds and pence but in the cost to the environment.
Luckily, I don't have to do the maths or the science because someone's already done that, Gareth Edward Jones from Bangor University.
Gareth, am I in for a surprise?
You might be, because I think lots of people think that food miles, the distance that food travels, is the biggest cause of the emissions.
But lots of other things happen in the food chain that also produce greenhouse gases.
So, we look at all of these and bring them down into one unit, which we call kilograms of carbon dioxide equivalent, which lets us make comparisons between different food chains.
Let's take an example.
What about these tomatoes?
These are British tomatoes and these are imported.
Most British tomatoes will be grown in greenhouses.
The growers put heat in to get the plants to grow well.
So, amongst vegetables, tomatoes are quite high.
They have a measurement of somewhere between two and five, depending where they're grown.
What about these Spanish ones?
They come straight in lorries to the UK and those lorries emit greenhouse gases.
But, actually, surprisingly they emit fewer greenhouse gases, up to about 3.5.
Right.
But it's not that simple, we're not just concerned about greenhouse gases.
This tomato is about 99.9% water and Spain hasn't got much water.
British apples here.
Yeah, British apples, fresh off the tree in October would be about the lowest footprint you could hope for.
They would be about 0.1, 0.15 kilograms of carbon dioxide.
What about this time of year when they're being kept in cold storage?
You can store British apples for about nine months.
At nine months, it would have doubled.
People like green beans all year round.
These are from Kenya.
What about these?
What's their tally?
A kilogram of beans would have, I'm afraid, an emission of five to nine which is amongst the highest of all vegetables.
Gareth, you're starting to make me think that to help save the world, I should stop eating fruit and veg.
That's exactly what we shouldn't be saying.
Here's one thing.
A portion of beans, which, let's say is about that much, by driving your car seven miles, you will have emitted more carbon dioxide than flying that amount of beans into the UK.
So, we need to get these things into perspective.
But, in years to come, we may not have to heat greenhouses or fly in as much fruit and vegetables.
Global warming could make our choice of British produce look very different.
These walnuts didn't grow in the south of France, or Turkey, or China.
They grew here in this orchard, in Kent.
Could they be a crop of the future, do you think?
I hope so.
That's what I believe so that's why I planted them.
Is it because the temperatures are rising a bit?
That's my bet.
And with 14 acres of walnut trees reaching maturity, it's a bet he hopes will really come good.
If all of those scientists who believe in climate change are proved to be correct, that could open a whole new world here in this country, not just walnuts, but many of what we now consider to be exotic fruits and vegetables could be home-grown, all year round.
For now, though, it's a choice between sticking to genuinely seasonal British food, or pay the environmental price for the alternatives.
That was gorgeous.
Very good.
I wonder what John's going to bring for breakfast.
I don't know.
But mushrooms would be good.
Why?
Well, on the theme of the van.
It's not mushroom coloured, it's nude!
Thank you.
Right.
What are you doing now?
I'm off to go and see some foals.
Are you?
Can you do us a favour?
What's that?
Look after my pan.
OK.
I'll see you later.
Have fun.
See you in a bit.
While Matt goes to see some foals, I'm hoping to find some birds.
Later on our trip through the New Forest, we'll be catching up with our breakfast guests.
Adam's put some camels through their paces but will he back them to make his fortune?
And Katie's been abandoned in a dark forest, with only the stars to guide her.
Nearly half the birds in the New Forest National Park are ground-nesting, which means they're particularly vulnerable and susceptible to those with heavy feet.
So, I'd better mind my step.
Spring is the start of the breeding season for ground-nesting birds.
I'm joining Andy Page from the Forestry Commission who monitors them and wants to show me a lapwing nest.
But they're so well camouflaged, even he struggles to find it.
Just stay where you are.
Don't put your foot anywhere.
You can just see the eggs there.
Look at that.
We were standing right over them.
See them just there?
Very vulnerable.
Yes, very.
They've got all the natural predation that can go on here.
Crows and foxes and all that.
When those chicks hatch, they can run around straight away but they don't fledge for another four or five weeks.
They're sitting pray.
They're very easy to be disturbed by dogs or people off the tracks and stuff.
We'll move away.
Andy won't let us stay by the nest for long as the anxious parents are hovering above.
While they return to the nest, he wants to show me an even rarer sight.
If I said to you now, there's a ground-nesting bird here with chicks within a few feet of us.
Can you see it?
Chicks?
Yes, chicks.
Where?
Oh.
Wow.
That's extraordinary.
You're looking at three chicks that are so close to fledging.
We say to people, come and enjoy the forest but through these really critical spring months, be aware that these birds are nesting on the ground and keep to the main tracks at these important times.
It's lovely to see the birds sitting on their nests in spring.
And first thing tomorrow, Matt and I are planning to be up super-early to record the dawn chorus.
The New Forest is home to all sorts of wildlife but none is more iconic than the New Forest pony.
And at this time of year they're starting to foal.
I'm riding out with Jonathan Garelli, the Head Agister, a kind of warden in the forest.
One of his roles is to keep a watchful eye on the animals.
Some of the mares you can see have lost a bit of condition through the winter.
We've had a very tough winter and the grass is finally starting to come through and they will pick up in condition very quickly.
And at what age then would you start foaling?
Probably the mares wouldn't generally get in foal, begin to foal until they're four or five-years-old.
We do occasionally get a three-year-old and sometimes even a two year-old to have a foal but that is quite rare.
Do you find that they need a bit of help?
No.
It's quite marvellous, really.
The ponies need very little interference from us.
They generally go off and foal perfectly all right on their own.
There is always the odd occasion when we do need to intervene but that's very rare.
We've got one right in front of us there.
White face, white legs.
How old would this one be?
Coming up to nearly a week old.
Oh!
Have you gone all shy?
Yes, they stay very close to mum at that age.
They don't like to stray too far.
I've got one here just basking in the sunshine.
Hello.
Yes it's a little girl.
She's only about two or three days old.
Look at her!
If people are riding through and seeing the animals in the forest, this is about as close as you want to get.
You don't want to disturb them too much.
When they're born, it is all legs and head really, but it will very much change very quickly at the end.
As well as new life in the countryside, spring also sees the start of the outdoor activity season.
Increasingly it's an opportunity for inventive farmers to make a bit more extra money off their land.
Adam's been to get some tips on how he could diversify into something off the beaten track.
I'm a farmer because it's what I always wanted to be.
It's not just about trying to make a living, it's a way of life.
My business partner Duncan Andrews and I farm 1,200 acres of arable and have 650 ewes and that gives us a reasonable income.
At the risk of sounding like a whingeing farmer, the problem is with farming and the income it's just so unpredictable.
With the weather, our land can drought out or it can be too wet and wreck the harvest.
Then there is animal diseases like blue tongue and TB that can just wipe out our livestock.
What we really need to do is to look for incomes outside traditional farming.
That can, you know, boost our whole farming business.
Diversification is the buzz word that farmers apply to anything slightly off the main farming agenda.
From cheese making to lavender farming for perfumes.
I run a rare breeds farm park alongside the commercial farm, but Dunc and I are always looking for new opportunities, so today we're off to visit a few businesses not far from us.
Pull!
Rob Ireland's place is first.
He runs what sounds like a playground for grown-ups.
We do quite a few things here.
We do the clays, we do quad bikes, we do field archery, we do 4 x 4 off-road driving.
We do fly-fishing instruction and fly-fishing.
You name it, we try and do it.
Try and please everybody.
And what about with people coming along shooting?
Presumably a lot of them are novices.
Totally novices.
They've never seen a gun before in their lives.
They get a very full briefing from me.
An introduction to what it's all about.
Safety being paramount.
Dunc's a bit of a master.
Put him through his paces, Rob.
Let's see.
Do you want to show me how you can do can it?
Why not?
Pull!
Dust.
Right in the middle.
Brilliant.
Nothing wrong with that.
You can have a job if you want one.
He's mastered that.
Let's go and have a go at something else, shall we?
This is the golf buggy.
We going for a round of golf?
Yes, if you want but it's a golf buggy with a difference.
If you come round this side, guys, I'll quickly explain to you what it's all about.
One of you is going to sit this side and you'll operate the golf buggy with your right foot.
Whoever's sitting this side will operate the steering.
But it's not quite as straightforward as you think!
'The golf buggy has been modified.
'When I turn left, it goes right and vice-versa.
'Perfect for a naturally terrible driver like me.'
Yes!
We've got it now!
That's absolutely brilliant, Rob.
It's just a little bit different, isn't it?
It's mad!
How on earth did you get into this game then?
Under pressure from the banks, really.
End of the 80s, farming turned a bit nasty for us.
I had a phone call from the bank manager at eight one evening to say that I had to reduce my overdraft.
I said, "By how much?"
He said, "By half."
I said, "When?"
And he said, "Now."
So that spurred me on to thinking about other things and we've done the clay shooting and that is my sport and I'd done a little bit of teaching and I thought there's a bit of an opportunity for a business.
For somebody considering setting out on a diversification project, what advice have you got?
You've got to think forward a little bit.
Do a bit of market research - see what's out there and what people are looking for.
If you can come up with something that's a bit quirky then there's a market coming in.
Are you going to retire and buy that pad in Barbados?
I'd love to but not for a few years yet, I don't think.
Rob has clearly made a success of his business but I asked the NFU's Phil Bicknell if the bigger picture was as positive.
We had about 3,000 farm businesses diversify for the first time last year, but we also had 3,000 diversified businesses stop trading.
But ultimately it adds money to the bottom line of farming.
Round about £300 million last year in England was added to agriculture's value because of diversified farm businesses.
Beef and arable farmer Ian Branston has found another unusual way of making some extra money from his land.
Hill rolling is a non-spectator extreme activity for which the rolling hills of the Cotswolds are perfect.
How did this all come about then, Ian?
It came about by a couple of lads driving along that road and spotting this hill, and then tracking me down at asking if they could roll their balls down it which I was obviously delighted with!
And is it much impact on the field, on the grass?
Absolutely no impact on the grass at all.
I think it's a thing locally for the community.
It's great because people come from miles around drinking in the local pubs and use the shops and everything else, so it's fantastic that way.
And when they are not rolling their balls down the hill our cattle are grazing it.
Is it a money-making venture?
It is probably my most profitable field on the farm.
By the same token I'm obviously not going to retire on it.
But it's a very valuable extra income for the farming enterprise.
This is something we're going to have to try out and I've got a bad back.
Me too.
So, Dunc, you're the man for the job.
Let's get you in there.
'Duncan leaps in, quickly followed by a bloke called Pete 'who we persuaded to be Dunc's sphere buddy.'
Maybe we should just let it down!
Woo-hoo!
Oh, my God.
Yow!
Let's go!
How was it, lads?
Really good.
You don't feel sick?
Not at all.
Do you want to go again?
I...maybe....
I've got an overdue library book to get back.
Otherwise I'd love to!
What a great sport.
This is fantastic.
I'm loving it.
Whoa!
Wild.
'Dunc's a little dizzy after that experience so he's left me to go 'and see the final potential money-spinner on my own.'
Joe and Rebecca Fossett run a camel racing business.
If you're holding an event, then you can hire these guys to come and entertain the crowds.
Joe, I've never seen anything like it in the Cotswold hills before.
Unbelievable.
It's certainly different, isn't it?
Amazing!
What's it like working with camels?
I've never stroked a camel before.
Oh, fantastic.
These camels are absolutely brilliant, they really are.
It depends on the training and handling.
I've been a long, long time getting these animals like this.
It takes a long time, a lot of training.
They're completely different to anything else you've ever trained.
The couple have six camels.
Each with very different characters.
Everybody loves Kokoso.
In fact he's had a play written about him, he gets fan mail and actually we're thinking of him standing as a Member of Parliament because I think he'd get more votes than most of the MPs!
You have to hold a dangerous wild animals licence to own camels, so this isn't a business to be undertaken lightly and come spring these animals need to get back into their training schedule.
After a winter of taking it easy, they need a bit of persuasion.
Come on!
Look at them go!
THEY LAUGH Come on!
Is there any money in camel racing?
Well, there's enough to make it worthwhile, I suppose.
Half of it is the entertainment value, isn't it?
Look at that!
Oh, Gobi, you always win because you are so greedy!
What a good boy!
'An easy winner.
It's been an interesting fact-finding day for Dunc and me.
'The golf buggy could easily be a hit with the kids at our farm park.
'I'd love to own a sphere and try hill rolling.
'But I love animals, so....'
How am I going to break the news to Dunc that I need to buy a couple of racing camels?
This is Roydon Woods on the fringe of the New Forest and it's a peaceful, tranquil and somehow secret spot.
And now we want to hear from you.
What do you feel is the perfect place in Britain that sums up all that is unique about our British countryside?
Yes, over the next few weeks we want you to share your secrets with us.
We want your nominations for Secret Britain, for a place that's special to you, that you feel represents the hidden best of our British countryside.
It might be a remote mountain retreat or the soft falls of a limestone valley.
A tumbling waterfall or a deserted beach which is special to you and your family.
A spectacular view or a stunning location for watching wildlife.
We're not looking for the tourist spots that everyone goes to.
We want to hear about those hidden places that are special just to you.
And we want to know not just where, but why?
What is it about your special place that makes it so extraordinary for you?
And which makes it represent the very best of the secret beauty of the British countryside?
Over the summer months, we'll be filming the length and breadth of the UK to show the British Isles at their best.
But we need your nominations to see which of our hidden landscapes will find their way into these very special programmes.
E-mail your thoughts with photos too if you want at...
You'll find all the information you need on the Countryfile website.
Time to head to the campsite and check out our accommodation for the night.
What is that?
There she is.
Wow.
That is my pod.
You're kidding.
This is where you're staying, is it?
Yes.
I can't believe it.
You're going to like this.
First the van and now this.
Come inside.
Look at the butchers!
Oh, gosh.
Most importantly for me, coal burning stove.
This is incredible, isn't it?
Got to have music.
Oh, you've got a gramophone!
Nice comfy bed.
Oh, that's so lovely!
John...
Yes?
To watch over me.
Amazing, isn't it?
Do you like the little stars up there?
Beautiful.
This is massive.
What are you sleeping in, then?
Right.
It looks very complicated.
D'you think that's the door?
OK.
So your poles go straight there like curtain rings?
That's it.
That's the top.
Right.
I tell you what.
If you just hang there for a second.
Just wait there.
You can't open the door.
Get out.
Get out of my pod!
Out!
It's my pod!
You're a boy!
You didn't even know what glamping was.
Oh dear!
Right, I'm not giving you any more help.
Good luck with that.
'Hmmph!
That's it from me.'
Oh dear.
'Wonder how he's getting on by himself?'
'Easy peasy.'
It'll be lovely sleeping out under the stars tonight.
Yes.
Mind you, you're not exactly roughing it, are you?
The important thing is it's a good time of year to star-gaze.
With temperatures on the rise as we head towards the height of spring and the evenings still dark, this is a great time of year to go star-gazing.
Sadly, for most of us, when we look up at night, its a blank canvas.
These satellite images demonstrate the problem.
Because we leave so many bulbs burning, our view of the stars is obscured by light pollution.
For 90% of the British population, the best way of seeing the many galaxies out there is by visiting a planetarium like this one in Glasgow.
They're great places for a basic lesson in how to star spot in the great outdoors, and astronomer Steve Owens is my tutor.
That is Orion, isn't it?
Those three?
Am I right?
That's right.
This is Orion's belt up here.
Orion is one of the most recognisable constellations in the sky and Orion is a great constellation to learn.
For example, if you go up and to the right of Orion's belt, you go through the V of the horns of Taurus the Bull and you get to this little cluster of stars here called the Seven Sisters.
In fact, this cluster has thousands of stars in it, but our eyes can only make out seven of them on a good clear night.
Going back to Orion's belt, we can use his belt and his left shoulder to go up across the sky towards these two bright stars, the Gemini twins, and at the moment, beside Gemini, we have very obviously the red dot of Mars.
Go in the opposite direction, we can find The Plough and these two stars in The Plough are pointers, and they point to the North Star.
So if you can find the North Star, stand facing it, you'll be facing north.
Fantastic.
Now, I have to remember all that information because I'm going to need it later.
It's amazing to think that we don't really get to see skies like this because of all the light in our cities.
You're right.
If you go outside in a city, you'll see 100, maybe 200 stars on a good clear night.
But compare that to the thousands of stars you see in a properly dark sky.
We were out last night measuring just how bright the skies above Glasgow are.
The reading we got was about 17 magnitudes per square arcsecond, which is just a measure of how bright the sky is.
So what would be total darkness?
Total darkness would be about 24 on that scale.
We can go to one of those places now, only a couple of hours' drive out of Glasgow.
Let's go.
With the sun sinking below to the Claterringshaws Loch, deep in the heart of Galloway Forest.
This is the UK's first Dark Sky Park and one of only five in the world and it's a haven for astronomers who want an unobscured view of the universe.
Galloway isn't the most remote place in the UK, but it's the perfect spot for a Dark Skies Park because it's close enough to Scotland's big cities to attract lots of visitors.
As night falls, I'm one astro-tourist getting quite excited.
Well, it's definitely past dusk now and it is well and truly night time.
If you look up into the sky, it is spectacular.
It's almost like there's too many stars up there in the sky.
It's unbelievable.
What we'll do is measure just how dark it is here and we'll compare that to the readings that Steve took in Glasgow yesterday.
To do that, we need to turn off these lights.
And use an infra-red camera.
Yesterday in Glasgow, it read about 17.
And here in the park, it's reading over 20.
And that's what you'd expect?
Absolutely.
In fact you can go to darker parts of the park and the very dark core of the park, that might read as dark as 21, 22.
'So, that's where we're going and I'm going to use the stars to navigate.'
Can you find north?
Well, I have to swing over this way.
There's The Plough.
It looks like it's in a different position...
And there's the Pole Star.
That's right.
'Fantastic.
I'm really getting into this astro-tourism.'
I thought I was going to be gardening and bird-watching in later life, but I think I might go for astronomy first.
A little bit cold.
'Steve is right.
It's absolutely freezing and completely, totally dark.'
'A few hundred yards further into the forest 'and the darkness claims its first victim.'
Oops!
S 'After recovering my composure and navigating my way further into the forest, a shadowy figure appears.'
What are we looking at?
Can you see the blur from the sky there?
Oh, look at that.
Yes, I can.
So you know what that is?
That's the Seven Sisters?
That's the Seven Sisters.
The projection of the night sky looked great in the planetarium but the real thing is just breathtaking.
How would you like to see the first signs of spring?
In the sky.
We can tell.
Well, you tell me.
Where is The Plough?
The Plough's there.
If you follow the droop down from the arm, that star over on the horizon there, the bright one that twinkles a little bit more, OK, is the first star that shows the beginning of spring arriving.
That's Arcturus and it's one of the first signs that spring's on the way.
Can you tell the seasons throughout the year by looking at the sky at night?
Absolutely.
The sky changes over the course of the seasons.
In the summer you get a group of stars called the Summer Triangle, which you can't see in winter.
And equally, Orion is out up at the moment but you can't see Orion in the summer.
It's a winter constellation.
You can't see it in the summer?
No.
'And this is what's on show tonight in Galloway Forest Park.'
How important is Dark Sky Park status to this area?
Everyone's enjoying the darkness around here.
It brings in people in the winter that wouldn't normally come.
They're staying here.
But the great thing is, they're all learning how good it is to have true darkness and how important it is to have true darkness for us and the wildlife and everything else around us.
And it really is a revelation.
As a city girl, it feels like light years since I've seen a sky like this.
Within just a few minutes of sky-gazing, I've seen The Plough and Mars, and a man-made treat, the international space station orbiting through the night sky, passing in front of Orion.
It's amazing to think that not so long ago, anyone could step outside their house at night and see skies like this.
But for most of us, there's somewhere dark enough to see the night sky just a few hours' drive away.
So I'd highly recommend a night trip to the countryside this spring.
Hiya.
Hi.
I understand it's going to be pretty cold tonight, so if you do happen to leave the keys to the camper under the plant pot, then I wouldn't object.
OK.
Right.
You sleep well.
See you in the morning.
Night.
It's just gone 5am, and since it's the weekend of International Dawn Chorus Day, it seems like the right time to record the birds here in one of the best places in the UK to listen to them.
We're up at this crazy hour, we're going to give the others, who are making their way over, the experience of waking up in the woodlands.
We certainly are.
So we'll record the dawn chorus.
Our sound man will help us do that with all sorts of special equipment.
Morning, Rob.
Morning.
We head off into the woods near the camp site to meet bird expert Nigel Matthews.
It sounds fantastic, doesn't it, already?
Rob positions the microphones as if he was recording an orchestra.
But why are they making all this noise?
It's like you singing, this is where you live and you don't want me to come...
Territorial song?
Territorial.
A bit of display as well, with the males saying, I'm a good songster.
Ready?
Yes.
Lovely.
Right, now, talk us through some of the sounds.
OK.
So it's ju-dit, ju-dit, ju-dit...
It's a song thrush.
And then we've got wren.
There's lots of trills and churs following each other.
We've had blackbirds, we've had robin, there's a willow warbler.
When they're all singing together it is very much like an orchestra, actually and you can't pick out individual instruments.
Is it particularly strong at this time of year?
Yes, April, May, it's just a fantastic time of year.
Really, really good.
And if you go to the Countryfile website, you can listen again to the New Forest dawn chorus in all its springtime glory.
Hello!
Anybody here?
I've seen a door, a chimney and topiary plants outside.
It's good, isn't it?
Guess which tent is Julia's!
'While we're enjoying the peace of the wood, there are intruders in the campsite.'
'But at least they've brought edible gifts.
I could murder a sausage!'
Are you a bit of a chef, John?
Yes, brilliant, I am.
Really?
No.
THEY LAUGH Invaders in our camp.
Hello, hello.
How did you know where we were?
'I've got a contribution from my travels too.'
What's he got there?
How about this for a little starter?
Smoked brown trout.
From just around the corner.
Eggs, Matt?
Yeah.
Oh, lovely.
Honey as well.
'As we start to tuck in, I've got an extra accompaniment for the meal, 'this morning's dawn chorus.'
So, do you know what they all are?
Can you tell us?
That's a song thrush.
Very good.
Oh, and that's a spotted Vauxhall Astra you can hear in the background.
That's bird-watching.
Lovely to listen to birdsong all day, but we've got a job to do.
We certainly have.
One of the New Forest Rangers has asked us if we'll give him a hand shifting some of his cattle to some fresh grass.
Julia and I are on a mission.
Local warden Michael Boxall and his son Martin are in charge.
Hi, Martin.
How are you doing?
Hello.
What's the plan?
We're going to move the cattle away from their wintering grounds.
They've been up here since December and we're going to start them on the round of the reserve.
They graze various parts through the year.
Throughout all the seasons, yes?
Yes.
We'll take them through the wood down to a meadow by the river.
Seven very pregnant cows about to give birth any day, and half a mile of woodland between them and the bottom pasture.
Easy.
Come on.
Come on, girls.
Shall we go for a little stroll?
Let's get up behind them.
'The cows were a bit reluctant to follow us, but John's on the case.'
Come on, John, get your arms out.
That red coat.
Come on.
Put a bit of pace into it.
'And it seems the cows aren't the only reluctant ones.'
Come on, Katie, come on.
Come on.
Galloping.
Oh, here we go.
There we go.
Now they're moving.
Who's bringing up the rear?
Oh, steady, steady.
There they go.
Come on.
Come on, girls.
Come on, girls, here we go.
It looks like the cows know where they're going.
Come on, girls.
Come on.
Steady down.
If you hear a big rumbling in a minute, just step to the side and let them go by.
Yes.
Giddy up, there.
I heard the rumble.
Steady!
Steady, there.
Are we taking this channel here, up to the left?
Going up there, yes.
Come on, girls.
Hang a left.
'It's all going swimmingly until the cows get their lefts and their rights mixed up 'and go completely off piste.
'Closely followed by Matt.'
It looks like they've run off, John.
A stampede over the hill.
Not our fault, though, is it?
I don't think so.
Just let them settle a little bit there, Jim.
They have gone completely the wrong way.
I think they're a bit star-struck, to be honest.
Matt Baker.
'They're soon back on track and heading towards their summer grazing.'
Come on, girls.
Steady, steady, there you go.
Ah, there we go.
They look like happy cows now, Michael.
Yes.
They're very happy cows, Julia.
See you later, Michael.
Thank you.
Enjoy the grass and happy calving!
A good job well done, don't you think?
That is it from the New Forest for our spring special.
We'll be back next week, business as usual on Sunday.
We'll see you then.
Bye bye.